我给你展示的这些特征
So these features that I'm showing you so
长期以来， Linux 已经建立在 Linux 中。
far have relatively been built
into Linux for a long time.
这些都是他们想要的内核的特征，就像我认为
These are features of the kernel they've
intended, like I think this has been
至少从 70 年代以来就像根已经过去了对吧
around at least since, like root has been
around since the 70s at least, right?
我认为名称空间最近略有增加，但
Namespaces I think
are slightly more recent, but
我想我们还是在说 2000 年的事你可能想看看我的情况
I think we're still talking 2000-ish,
you may wanna fact check me on that.
但我认为那是正确的。
But I think that's about right.
这最后一个是比较近的。
This last one is relatively recent.
它是在谷歌发明的。
It was invented at Google.
这叫控制组对吧
It's called control groups, right?
所以谷歌有一个问题是他们希望有多个不同的
So Google had a problem that they would
like be running multiple different
流程，他们会运行这些，就像彼此信任，对吧 ?
processes, they'd be running these,
and like they trust each other, right?
所以他们不担心就像偷别人的秘密
So they are not worried about like
stealing each others' secrets inside of
谷歌是吧
Google, right?
所以他们就像很酷的一样，我们只是在处理彼此之间的过程，你跑
So they were like cool, we're just running
processes right next each other, you run
您的 Web 服务器，我将运行我的 Web 服务器，我们不会有不同的 VM 表单，对吗 ?
your web server, I will run my web server,
we won't have different VMs form, right?
我们只会在有限的环境中拥有它们。
We'll just have them in their
like limited environments.
他们就像谷歌地图上的人一样
And they kinda had this problem though
like if someone on the Google Maps
团队要跑了，可能就像 Google Docs 团队的过程，
team were to run away process, that might
kill like the Google Docs team's process,
，对， cuz 杀了整个服务器，对吧 ?
right, cuz it kills the entire server,
right?
所以他们想做的就是想限制
So what they wanted to do is
they wanted to limit how much
这些过程中有一个可以访问的资源，对吗 ?
resources that one of these processes
would have access to, right?
基本上说，你看，你得到一个核心，或者你有 10% 的 CPU 和
And basically said like, look, you get
one core, or you get 10% of this CPU and
一旦你退出了我很抱歉这些都是你的错对吧
then once you're out of that,
I'm sorry, that's all you get, right?
库兹我不会让你毁了另一个小组的程序对吧
Cuz I'm not gonna let you crash this
other team's running process, right?
所以他们想出了这个控制小组的想法。
So they came up with this
idea of control groups.
我觉得以前有另外一个名字，
I think there was another name for
it previously,
实际上他们把它叫做容器，就是他们所称的。
actually they called it containers,
is what they called it.
但后来，他们开始申请的不仅仅是控制团体。
But then they, that kinda started
applying to more than just control group.
所以他们把那个改成了 C 组对吧
So they changed that to C groups, right?
这就是 C 组的意思是这样的想法
So that's what C groups are for,
it's this idea like,
我想限制你有多少 CPU ，你有多少内存。
I wanna limit how much CPU you have,
how much memory you have.
网络带宽有多大，就像有一堆你可以限制的东西。
How much network bandwidth, like there's
a bunch of stuff that you can limit on.
我们将会看到 CPU 和内存，但您可以为
We're just gonna be looking at CPU and
memory, but you can do control groups for
很多事情对吧
a lot of things, right?
所以它是从那里来的但是后来它变成了一个很酷的
So that's where it came from, but then it
turned out that this is a really cool and
有趣的想法，因为现在我可以做这些不共享的环境，
interesting idea, because now,
I can do these unshared environments,
然后我就可以给他们分配控制组了
and then I can assign
control groups to them.
而且现在我有了这些程序
And also now I have these
contained processes that can't do
除了我让他们做的事以外的任何事对吧
anything besides what I tell them to do,
right?
因此，您可以执行任意数量的代码并为所欲为。
So you can execute arbitrary amounts
of code and do whatever you want.
但你唯一能搞砸的人是你自己吧
But the only person that you're
gonna screw over is yourself, right?
你不能把其他任何人都搞砸了
You can't screw over anyone else and
这里有集装箱的概念
that's kinda the idea
with containers here.
那么，再一次，就像一个更真实的例子，如果我们要办一个托管服务，对吧 ?
So, again, like a more real life example,
if we're running a hosting service, right?
还有 Bob 和 Alice 在我们的主持下运行他们的服务器
And we have Bob and Alice that are running
their servers within our hosting
环境，我们不想让夏娃把它连接到环境里，
environment, we don't want it so that Eve
can connect it to the environment and
跟别人的过程搞混了吧
start messing with the other
people's processes, right?
她可以直接掉到 CPU 100 %的位置
She can just drop like something
that's gonna peg the CPU at 100%,
把他们的资源都带下来，对吧 ?
take all their resources, and
bring down their servers, right?
我们想防止这种事发生
We wanna prevent that kind
of thing from happening.
所以我们要有有限的物质资源，
So we need to have it so that it has
limited access to physical resources,
或物理，因为大多数容器仍在 VM 内运行，对吗 ?
or physical, because most containers
are still run within VMs, right?
这里有多种级别的虚拟化。
There's multiple levels
of virtualization here.
但为了所有目的和目的我们会叫这些物质资源
But for all intents and purposes,
we'll call these physical resources,
有多少 CPU，多少 RAM，这些东西。
how much CPU, how much RAM,
those sorts of things.
好的，所以我说这个有点难
Okay, so I'll say that like this
is a little bit more difficult to
比我们以前做的那些技术更技术性的事情要完成的事情
accomplish than the things we've done
before that's more technical in nature.
所以我请你和我有点小熊
So I invite you to just kind
of bear with me a little bit.
所以我们要做的第一件事就是
So the first thing we need
to do is we need to say apt,
这还在我们的 Ubuntu VM 或容器中。
this is again still within
our Ubuntu VM or container.
Apt get install ，然后我们说 -y， cgroup-tools 和
Apt get install, then we say -y,
cgroup-tools and
我们还会安装 htop 和一些有趣的游戏
we're gonna install htop as well for
some fun later.
而且这两个都不是很大的。
And neither one of those is very big.
我们刚刚安装的是我最喜欢的工具之一，这实际上是给
So we just installed htop which is one of
my favorite tools, this'll actually give
你的电脑现在的情况很直观
you a nice visualization of what's
going on with your computer right now.
所以就算是这个集装箱我觉得我的电脑上有八芯
So even this container, I think my
computer has eight cores on it or
六芯或类似的东西
six cores or something like that.
您可以看到此容器及其自身使用的 cgroups
You can see that this container in and
of itself using cgroups
实际上只有在技术上能接触到两个，这很有趣。
only actually has technically access
to two, which is kind of interesting.
我有八条 RAM
And I have eight gigs of RAM.
这只真正能访问 1.95 gigs 的 RAM。
This one only actually has
access to 1.95 gigs of RAM.
所以实际上是用 cgroups 来完成这个，对吗 ?
So it's actually using cgroups
to accomplish this, right?
这个小容器什么都看不到
This little container
can't see anything else.
好了不干了不干了
Okay, quit, quit, quit, okay.
这就是 htop 的意思，我很喜欢，它是一个有趣的工具
So that's what htop is,
I quite like, it's a fun tool and
你也可以在麦克上使用
you can use it on Mac as well.
好吧我们要做的第一件事就是用 cgcreate -g
Okay, so the first thing we're gonna
do is we're gonna say cgcreate -g.
我们将创建一个新的控制组，就是这样做的。
And we're gonna create a new control
group, that's what this does.
而且它会限制在 cup.memory 上
And it's gonna limit on cpu.memory io
你就能输入金发美女和冰柜好吗
which you type blkio.devices and
freezer, okay?
然后我们会说 :/sandbox
And then, we're gonna say :/sandbox.
好吧这为我们创造了一个新的 C 组
Okay, this creates a new C group for us.
所以我要回到我的另一个 Docker 容器
So I'm gonna come back over here
to my other Docker container.
我们要运行同样的不共享的环境
And we're gonna run that
same unshared environment.
事实上，我们可以在这里做，因为我已经从这里跑来了。
Actually, we can just do it from here
because I already ran it from here.
这一个
So this one.
所以我们要把其中一个重新回到一个不共享的环境中。
So we're gonna have one of these go
back into an unshared environment.
好吧跟我们之前的一样的命令
Right, All right,
exact same command that we ran before.
现在这只在一个不共享的环境下我要走了
So now this one is in an unshared
environment and now I'm gonna go and
其实是给这个分配一个小组来控制这个。
actually assign a cgroup to this,
to control this one.
现在你得从主机上运行，对吧 ?
Now, you have to run this from the host,
right?
你不能用这种方式来管理它，你不能说自己是对的吗 ?
You can't run it from with like,
you can't say limit myself right?
我得回去给主持人做。
I have to go back to the host and
do it from the host.
所以我还有一个，我可以在这里看到，我可以在这里看到我的不共享的批处理环境。
So I have another, I can see here, I can
see my unshared batch environment here.
这是我连接到同一个容器的另一个过程。
So this is another process that I
have connected to the same container.
所以我跑来了，我可以看到这里的这批号正在运行。
So I ran ps aux and I can see here
this batch right here is running.
所以我需要这个 PID 7607
So what I need is I need
this PID right here, 7607,
这对你的电脑是不一样的对吧
this will be different for
your computer, right?
把 PID 分配给 PID 是不一样的
Cuz how it assigns
the PID will be different
以你的电脑为基础
based on the computer you're running on.
所以我要你跑 ps
So I need you to run ps aux.
我要你去找这个混蛋这个
And I need you to find the bash,
this one here.
这可能是最高的吧，除非你有多重，对吧 ?
That's the highest one probably,
unless you have multiple, right?
你可以看到我有 104个
So you can see here I have 104.
104 可能是我现在正在做的
104 is probably the one that I'm
actually doing right now, or
可能是另一个
might have been the other one.
这不重要对吧
Doesn't matter, needs this one, right?
不分享就直接来了
It'll come directly
right after the unshare.
7607你就不一样了
So 7607, it'll be different for you.
现在我要你做的就是我要你说
And now what I want you to do
is I want you to say cgclassify
-g cpu，内存，blkio，设备，冷柜
-g cpu,memory,blkio,devices,freezer
:沙箱。
:sandbox.
如果您不知道，沙箱是我在此处创建的控制组的名称。
If you can't tell, sandbox is the name
of the control group I've created here.
你可以随便给它打个电话
You can call it whatever you want.
然后我会放 7607
And then I'm gonna put 7607.
所以现在这个巴什和它的所有孩子
So now, this bash and
all of its children processes,
对，因为进程会衍生其他进程。
right, because processes
spawn other processes.
他们都是过程树的一部分对吧
They're all part of a process tree, right?
我是说那个过程树里面的东西都在里面
I'm saying, everything inside of that
process tree is now inside of this
控制组。
control group.
现在这并不意味着什么，对，因为我什么都没做。
Right now that doesn't mean anything,
right, because I haven't done anything.
但我们要走了
But we're about to.
但如果你想看看里面到底是什么
But if you wanna see
what's actually in there,
我们可以说 cat/sys/fs/cgroup/cpu/sandbox/tasks 。
we can say
cat/sys/fs/cgroup/cpu/sandbox/tasks.
你可以在这里看到 7607，对吧 ?
And you can see here, 7607, right?
所以我们其实也可以直接加这个，但是
So we can actually just directly
add to that as well, but
这就是 CG 对我们的分类
that's what CG classify does for us.
就像在这个控制组里把它分类好吗
As it classifies that as inside
of this control group, okay?
所以我想看看有多少资源
So I want to see how
much resources it has so
我要说猫 /sys/fs/cgroup/cpu/sandbo/cpu.shares 。
I'm gonna say cat
/sys/fs/cgroup/cpu/sandbox/cpu.shares.
你可以看到它有 1024，这意味着它有一个核心，我相信。
You can see here it has 1024, which means
that it has access to a core, I believe.
不，这是优先事项，对吧 ?
No, this is the priority, right?
所以你可以说这是一个低优先级的控制组，对吧 ?
So what you can say is like this is
a low priority control group, right?
所以我可以说如果这就像五个
So I can say that if this was like a five,
任何一到 1024 的东西就会被放在上面
anything that was at 1024 would
get prioritized above it, right?
所以如果我有两个相互竞争的东西，就会比较他们的优先次序。
So if I have two competing things it'll
compare like what their priority is.
现在让我们来限制正在发生的事情，对吧 ?
Now let's get into actually
limiting what's happening, right?
所以我们要说 cgset -r cpu.cfs_period，
So we're gonna say cgset
-r cpu.cfs_period,
我请你复制并粘贴
I would invite you to just copy and
paste this,
我真的不明白这些东西的所有东西。
I actually really don't understand all of
the everything that's going on with these.
就像我说的控制小组在这里是我的薪水
Like I said control groups are kind
of above my pay grade here.
但是 100000 -r
But 100000 -r
cpu.cfs_quota。
cpu.cfs_quota.
所以我们要做的就是尝试
So what we're doing here
is we're gonna try and
将其限制为仅使用可用 CPU 的 10% ，对吗 ?
limit this to only use 10%
of the available CPU, right?
所以我的容器里有 10% 的东西
So it's actually gonna be 10% of
what's available in my container,
或该容器可使用的两个核心的 10% 。
or 10% of the two cores that this
container has available to it.
等式然后我们就把这个
Equals and
then we're gonna subshell this out
五千次，甚至可能是百分之五。
to 5000 times, this might even be 5%.
我认为这可能是 5 %。
I think this might be 5%.
getconf N，即空间， NPROCESSORS。
getconf N, that's a space, NPROCESSORS.
那就是沙箱的问题了
And that's gonna be for sandbox.
好吧我知道这是命令的一团糟
Okay, so I recognize that
that's a mess of a command.
但这里的想法是这个特殊的 c 组，我们说，哎，
But the idea here is this
particular c group, we said, hey,
此树中的任何内容都只能使用可用处理能力的 5% 。
anything inside of this tree, it can only
use 5% of the available processing power.
好吧那我们再多做一次
Okay, and
then we're gonna do one more cgset,
这只会让人更容易理解
this one's a little bit
easier to understand,
cgset -r memory.limit_in_bytes= ，我们会说
cgset -r memory.limit_in_bytes= and
we're gonna say,
这个可以有 80 兆的，对吧 ?
this has access to 80 megabytes, right?
以上都是内存不足的问题。
Anything above that,
it just runs out of memory.
我们会说沙箱，好的，然后我们可以来看看。
And we're gonna say sandbox, Okay,
and then here we can check it out.
我们可以说， cgget -r memory.stat 用于沙箱。
We can say,
cgget -r memory.stat for sandbox.
这会输出很多东西但是
And this'll output a bunch of stuff, but
我们可以看到这就是它的实际极限
we can see here this is the physical
limit of what it could go to, but
我们是说，哎，这个是八十兆字节的，对吧 ?
we're saying, hey, this is what 80
megabytes would be in bytes, right?
这仅能访问 80 兆字节。
This only has access to 80 megabytes.
好了现在我要说的是我们可以看的
Okay, so now I'm gonna say htop just so
we can watch.
现在我的容器里没有很多东西对吧
Right now there's not a lot
going on in my container, right?
你可以看到这里有 PS 的牛。
And you can see this is
the PS ox down here.
现在，我希望您回到 Docker 容器中。
So now I want you to go back
into your Docker container here.
我要给你演示如何把一个 CPU 锁在一个有趣的问题上，对吧 ?
And I'm gonna show you how to
pin a CPU just for fun, right?
现在我不建议在这里放置叉式炸弹
Now, I don't recommend
dropping a fork bomb in here,
你得多做点东西来防止叉式炸弹
you have to do a bit more stuff to
prevent fork bombs from taking over your
因为他们工作的方式
computer because of how they work.
所以别那么做
So don't do that.
除非你想把你的电脑撞向我的客人
Unless you want to crash your
computer in which case be my guest.
在 Linux 中我最喜欢的东西是你可以做的
So one of my favorite things
in Linux is you can do yes and
它只会永远重复 Y ，对吗 ?
all it does it just repeats Y forever,
right?
或者你可以说 " 是" 废话现在说的是 " 无限的废话 "
Or you can say yes, crap and
now it just says crap infinitely.
所以如果我说的是 /dev 空，那只是虚惊一场
So if I say yes into /dev null,
which is just a scream into the void
基本上就是这个指令的价值
basically that's the equivalent
of what this command is.
这事要做的就是把中央的 CPU
What this is gonna do,
is it's going to pin the CPU for
这个特殊的过程，对吧 ?
this particular process, right?
它会用尽可能多的 CPU
It's gonna take as much
CPU as it possibly can.
所以如果回到这里来 Docker 的话，你可以在这里看到 12%的情况。
So if go back over here to Docker,
you can see here it's taking about 12%.
在哪里，对，就在那里，对吧 ?
Where is the, yes,
it's right there, right?
如果这不是里面的问题这会彻底把我们的 CPU 锁在里面
Now if this wasn't inside of this,
this would totally pin the CPU for us,
对，百分之百。
right, 100%.
但因为我们使用 C 组
But because we're using C groups,
它保存在这个特定的秘密里
it's keeping that contained within
this one particular secret.
太酷了对吧
That's pretty cool, right?
我们人为地限制了这一过程。
We've artificially limited
this particular process.
尽管它正试图把我们搞砸，但我们只是说没有。
And despite the fact that it's trying
to screw us over, we just say nope.
你唯一能做的就是把所有东西都带走
The only thing you can do is you can
take everything inside of here and
你可以烧了它
you can burn that.
然后你就运气好了
And then you're just
out of luck after that.
太酷了
Cool.
所以，我们也要为记忆做个工作。
So let's do it for the memory too.
别再说了我们会用 S 的但我们要做点什么
Stop that and we'll say, We're gonna use
the S again, but we're gonna do some
更让人感到不安的是，老实说，我不明白到底发生了什么。
more fanciness, which honestly, I don't
understand exactly what's going on here.
我把这个 100% 的人拉下来就像我的大部分代码一样
I pulled this 100% off of stack
overflow like most of my code.
但这将会消耗尽可能多的内存。
But this is going to consume as
much memory as it possibly can.
这里的想法是不断地填满我们的记忆直到它耗尽
The idea here is it's going to continually
fill our memory until it runs out of
内存。
memory.
所以，如果我们回到我们的交换中，再回顾一下。
So again,
if we look back back here at our hswap.
你可以在这里看到，我们的内存使用量也有很大的增长，对吧 ?
You can see here, our memory
usage went up quite a bit, right?
但它有 1.95 千兆字节的 RAM
But this has 1.95 gigabytes worth of RAM,
and
只消耗了 80 兆字节对吧
it's only consuming about
80 megabytes of it, right?
你可以在这里看到，我想它会显示它，有一个 CPU 百分比。
So you can see here, I think it'll
show it, there's a CPU percentage.
我可以向下滚动，你可以。
Can I scroll down, there you can.
你可以看到它消耗了 3.2% 的内存量，对，
So you can see here it's consuming
3.2% ish worth of memory, right,
这不是很多，对，我们只局限于 80 兆字节。
which is not a lot, right,
cuz we limited to only 80 megabytes.
事实上我没有给你看另一个
And actually, since I didn't show
you that with the other one,
让我们再一起去玩吧
let's run the other one again just for
fun.
我们会回到这个顶部，你可以看到 CPU 在 10%的位置。
We'll go back over here to this htop and
you can see the CPU here pegged at 10%.
所以我们基本上是用手创造了一个容器，对吧 ?
So we basically created
a container by hand, right?
不是完全的，你还需要 Docker，相信我。
Not totally,
you still need Docker, believe me.
但这基本上是 Docker 实现的目标
But this is essentially what
Docker is accomplishing for
你在车篷下面对吧
you underneath the hood, right?
对于您，它也会为您提供更多信息，例如，创建卷和网络，以及
Again it does more for you there
like create volumes and networks and
帮你管理一堆东西
manage a bunch of stuff for you.
但在它的核心，容器系统就是这样。
But at its core,
the container system is this.
>那么 Docker 将处理所有 C 组吗 ?
&gt;&gt; So Docker will handle all the C group?
> > 是。
&gt;&gt; Yep.
我要说大多数使用 Docker 的人员不知道 C 组是什么。
I would say most people that use
Docker don't know what C groups are.
你永远不会知道的对吧
[LAUGH] Cuz you never have to know, right?
它只为你管理这些东西
It just manages all that stuff for you.
所以现在你可以像个斯诺克的球衣了
So now you can go and
be like snooty jerks to your obstacles,
就像我知道 cgroups 是什么，然后就走了。
like I know what cgroups are and
then just walk away.
这就是我要做的
That's what I would do.
我应该在这停车
I probably should stop this over here.
所以就为了搞笑
So, just for funsies.
让我们尝试一下，是的，现在我不在我的环境改变之外。
Let's try this, yes into, so at now I'm
outside of my change of environment.
如果我说 " 是 " / " 是 / "/ " 空" 。
And if I say yes into/dev/null.
这可能很痛苦
This might be painful.
你可以在这里看到，它完全是固定在其中一个核心。
You can see here,
it's totally pinning one of these cores.
因为现在是在群外，对吧 ?
Because now it's outside of the cgroups,
right?
再一次，如果我们回去再看看，它应该是没有固定的。
And again, if we go back and
look again, it should be unpinned.
这就是我们要用手动方式手动创建容器的问题。
So this is as far as we're going to go
with manually creating containers by hand.
我今天给你展示的一切都是学术性的活动
LIke everything that I've shown you so
far, this has been an academic exercise so
你知道 Docker 会为你做什么
that you understand what Docker
is actually going to do for you.
其他的我们要用更高的
For the rest of the class,
we're going to be using higher
能帮你管理这些东西的工具
level tools that's just gonna
manage all this stuff for you.
我也不认为你真的需要知道我给你看的这些东西
Again, I don't think you really ever need
to know these things that I've shown you,
但现在你知道了到底发生了什么
but now that you do you know
exactly what's happening.
我想如果你明白你的工具的复杂性
And I think again, if you understand
the complexity of your tools,
你拥抱他们对吧
you embrace them, right?
现在，您了解 Docker 正在执行的操作
Now you understand that
what Docker is doing for
你你会很感激有人花了时间
you, you're gonna be a lot more
grateful that someone took the time to
构建 Docker，对吧 ?
build Docker, right?
相反，下次您遇到 Docker 问题时，
Rather than,
next time you have a Docker problem,
你就可以把你的笔记本扔了
you can just wanna throw your laptop.
至少你会有点感激的
At least you'll be a little bit grateful.